- So I'm Pam Gutman.
I'm the Regional Director for Advanced Transportation
for the California Community Colleges here in the Bay Area.
What that means is I work with the transportation programs
for the colleges that have programs in aviation,
automotive, and in drones.
And this morning we're gonna be talking about
advanced air mobility.
And this is an area that I particularly
have a great passion for.
I have been extraordinarily lucky
to be working in the field of transportation
because transportation has been absolutely transforming
before our very eyes.
And we are so fortunate today to have three
of our partners in advanced air mobility to share with you
what they're doing in the world of eVTOLs
and autonomous aircraft.
Some of which seem like out of another age completely,
but they are getting very, very close
to joining the other aircraft in the sky.
And for our students, this is a tremendous opportunity
to partner with people who are pioneers
in absolutely new technology and new aircraft.
And it's our good fortune to have them with us today
to share with us the skills that our students are going
to need to be successful in those careers going forward.
Because what we're preparing them for now comes close,
but not quite the whole ball of wax
or what they need for careers going forward.
So today we are very lucky to have with us three employers,
Pyka, who is in Alameda
and quite close by to my home college.
And she's working in the area of advanced aircraft
that's autonomous and working
and providing crop dusting services autonomously.
And they're doing that currently in certain countries
around the world and soon in our own backyards.
And then we have both Joby and Wisk Aero
who are very, very close to getting
all of what they need in the area of eVTOLs.
And they're gonna explain all that to you.
And I'm hopefully gonna sign up for one
of the first rides ever in that area.
I'm very excited.
They don't know that, but I'm gonna do that.
And then we have UC Berkeley here with us today
because I found out not too long ago
that UC Berkeley's doing some exciting things
in the world of advanced transportation.
And they're going to hopefully be working with us,
partnering with the community colleges in this capacity.
Because I see tremendous opportunity for us
to work together going forward
because we're gonna be sharing our skill sets,
our knowledge, and our students with them.
'Cause some of our students hopefully,
will go on to UC Berkeley, let's hope.
I also have with us today DART,
which is the drone and robotic technology initiative
who I got to meet a couple of years ago
and was absolutely blown out of the water
when I went to their LIFT Summit this past March.
Because they brought in everybody from the world
of advanced air mobility
and it was extremely exciting and thrilling.
And they're doing tremendous work
for our students in the workforce development field.
So today we have Josh Metz from DART
who's going to be moderating the panel this morning.
And I'm gonna turn it over to Josh.
- All right.
All right, Pam, thank you very much.
And thank you, yeah.
(attendees applaud)
Yeah.
It was great to have you at the LIFT Summit
and get a chance to make this connection
with the Bay Area Community College Consortium
and now the California group.
And I'm gonna open with a little overview
of where DART is coming from.
And let me see if I can get that to come up on the screen.
Give me one moment here.
And then I'll turn it over to our panelists.
The reason I'm gonna talk about DART
is that that we indeed have been working
in the field of advanced air mobility.
And really the integration of emerging capabilities
and autonomy, electrification
and how those converge to deliver
growth opportunities in a variety of sectors.
So this is our DART board
and the blue lines there indicate some of the areas
that we've seen opportunity since starting this work
really back in 2017.
We were involved with the redevelopment
of Fort Ord down in Monterey County,
and saw some things happening
that pointed us in this direction.
And so we have, we're a public benefit corporation
and we have programs in workforce development,
infrastructure and ecosystem.
So a lot of what we do is connect with industry,
academia, government and community based organizations
to realize the opportunities
that these emerging technologies represent.
And so that's some of the background.
One of the, we have the Joby aircraft up there on the right
because Joby has found a home at the form of Fort Ord
with their manufacturing operations.
And that was really one of the catalysts
for our involvement.
But you can see that, you know,
what's really compelling for,
from the standpoint of rural California
and counties outside the Bay Area
is that there's opportunities in this emerging sector
as along with the traditional hubs in the Bay Area.
So we focus a lot on that.
And you know, I just wanna point out that, you know,
while Pam indicated there are some technicalities
in terms of future certification of aircraft
to carry people.
There's a lot going on, as you well know,
in existing applications of autonomous systems,
drones for different use cases.
You hear about it in the news all the time.
And certainly the national security apparatus
is the largest market,
but we, there's huge potential for good.
And so infrastructure inspection,
wildfire response and support,
moving people and in agriculture.
So those are the Joby, Wisk and Pyka aircraft
down there below.
So those are things to pay attention to
for your students and your programs.
And we have identified,
especially in the advanced air mobility category,
these opportunities for community college.
You know, certainly moving into four year
and the engineering degree pathway is well understood,
but we have found that there's a huge need
for all kinds of technical, technician roles
in advanced manufacturing,
electric aircraft maintenance,
aerospace and ground operations
and field operations among others.
And to make this all work, especially for the moving
of people and goods,
there's gonna be new infrastructure required.
So all of that is opportunity for our community
and the community college has a huge role to play in that.
I just wanted to call out two recent funding awards
that the state of California has made in terms
of supporting the growth of this sector.
One is a large award to the University of California
natural resources, $15 million across the state
to support the movement towards improved
ag tech integration.
And so one of the components of that is a whole curriculum
for drone education.
We find that the drone education
is really the gateway drug
for aerospace today.
And so it's a great way to engage students at an early age.
Down in the Monterey Bay Area in the Central Coast,
there was another big award made $7.5 million dollars
to support the growth
of an air mobility innovation corridor
that will link general aviation airports
to existing nodes to further the capabilities
of the companies represented here
to develop and test and expand in California.
That's all really important for retaining jobs
and growing our economy.
So if you wanna hear more about this, Pam mentioned it,
our LIFT Summit is in March of next year
and we'd love to have more community college folks involved.
And so with that I'd like to turn to our esteemed panel,
which is an incredible group of people and companies
and education providers that you'll hear from.
And I'll pass it next to Monisha White from Pyka
to do a little introduction and tell you about herself
and her company and then we'll get into some Q&A
as we get into it.
Thank you.
(attendees applaud)
You can pull your guy up there.
- All right.
Hi, everyone.
I am really excited to be here to talk to you about Pyka.
Pyka is a robotics company on a mission
to build the most useful autonomous aircraft on Earth.
I wanna start with a video
so you can actually see our planes in action.
- [Narrator] Pyka was founded in 2017 by four entrepreneurs
with a vision to bring society a safer, cleaner,
and more cost-effective form of transportation
enabled by autonomous electric aircraft.
But to get there, we have taken a very different
approach than most.
First, we gave up on the vertical takeoff
and landing requirements of past aircraft we have developed
in order to dramatically simplify our products
and increase their range.
And second, we wanted to bring
an autonomous electric aircraft to market
as fast as humanly possible.
So we targeted use cases that have an inherent tolerance
of risk and an immediate need for innovation.
We started with the most dangerous commercial aviation
mission on Earth, which is crop dusting.
And then the question for us was,
can we actually show an end-to-end proof
of these autonomous electric capabilities
really demonstrate their significance to customers?
So that is exactly what we did.
We identified the requirements for the market
and designed an extremely innovative product
to fit those requirements that incorporates just dozens
of proprietary technologies ranging from batteries
to motor controllers to motors,
and the entire flight control stack
in avionics underneath that.
We then secured precedent setting regulatory approvals
for the aircraft, which allows us
to operate commercially in the United States,
in Brazil and much of Latin America.
We delivered to some of the biggest players in the market,
including Dole and Embraer.
And ramped production to roughly one aircraft per month
while racking up over 5,000 flights.
On top of that, we answered the market's demand
for a large scale zero emission cargo aircraft
by launching an exciting new product, Pelican Cargo.
Today we've delivered Pelican Cargo to customers
including the United States Air Force Research Lab
as well as Skyports' drone services.
And we managed to pull all of this off
with roughly $30 million spent.
With five years of commercial operation under our belt
and customers across three different continents,
Pyka is by far the leader in commercializing large scale
autonomous electric aircraft.
We're now rapidly scaling up production in the Bay Area
with an eye towards significant revenue growth
in the next couple of years
as well as a fast path to profitability.
(attendees applaud)
- I'm still going. (laughs)
So Pyka was founded in 2017 in the Bay Area.
The company actually started in Michael,
the CEO's parents' backyard in Stanford, California,
where our four co-founders built the very first prototype
of a Pyka plane that actually flew successfully.
We've now grown to around 80 employees
and we operate in a 110,000 square foot production facility
in Alameda Point.
So this is our whole team, our people and dogs
in our facility in Alameda.
We have, in addition to our production facility,
we have two test sites that are each about an hour away
and we are actively flying our aircraft
there every single day.
Our founders really wanted our products
to actually make a real world impact quickly.
We identified use cases that are very risky
and where our aircraft would have an immediate benefit
to our customers.
We started with crop dusting,
which is the most dangerous flight mission on Earth.
Just to give you a bit of a sense of this,
a pilot who has a 40 plus year career
as a crop duster has about a 15% chance of dying on the job.
We launched our agricultural aircraft as a safer,
cleaner and more cost-effective alternative
to the conventional crop dusting methods.
One, there's no pilot on board.
There is, it's zero emission.
It massively reduces the drift of the chemicals
that are spraying that can be really harmful
to neighboring communities and neighboring farms.
And it reduces the use of these chemicals up to 15%,
which in addition to being more environmentally friendly
is also creates significant cost savings.
In 2021, we then launched our Pelican Cargo,
which is the aircraft on the left.
It has about 80% shared commonality
with our agricultural aircraft.
So we reused a lot of the same design choices
and then made modifications to support the new use cases.
We created this product as a zero emission commercial
logistics platform designed to enable deliveries
of critical supplies to remote, rural
and hard to get to locations.
We're now actually expanding the capabilities
of our cargo aircraft
to support humanitarian disaster relief
and defense use cases as well.
We're actually excited to be launching the next generation
of Pelican Cargo soon.
So stay tuned for the launch of this aircraft.
On the regulatory side,
we've achieved industry first milestones.
Pyka today is the largest autonomous aircraft authorized
by the FAA for commercial use in the United States.
Additionally, we have a lot of overseas operations,
so we've also received comparable authorization
for commercial use in several other countries
including Brazil, Honduras,
Costa Rica and New Zealand.
And not only are we authorized to fly in the United States
commercially, we actually have our products in the hands
of customers and are doing real work around the world.
These are a few of the locations
where we have active customers
and our products are currently operating commercially.
The customers listed here are most
of our publicly announced customers.
We'll also be announcing a couple of,
actually a handful of additional customers
who haven't yet been disclosed in the coming months.
Right now we are gearing up to ramp up production in 2026
to satisfy a massive demand from our existing
and our new customers.
And then zooming out,
we really see industrial use cases as just the start.
In the future we aim to leverage our experience
and our expertise to then move into passenger carrying
autonomous aircraft as well.
We see the current operations that we're doing
as really extremely meaningful
and impactful in their own right.
And we also see these as positioning us really well
to expand into passenger carrying with thousands
and thousands of flights under our belt.
In order to support the production ramp up,
to support our customer,
increasing customer operations
and the continued development of our current
and new products,
we are hiring, we need to grow our team.
We're bringing on technicians, operators
and engineers across our teams,
and looking to bring them on in departments
including manufacturing and supply chain
in our flight operations.
Both test site at our local test sites
as well as deploying to our customer sites
and in engineering, in hardware engineering.
At Pyka, our mission really depends on talented people
as much as the cutting edge technology that we've developed.
And I'm really excited to be here to talk today about
how we can grow the workforce
that makes this future possible.
Thank you.
(attendees applaud)
- All right, thank you, Monisha.
Next,
I'll let Dr. Pavan
Yedavalli.
- You got it.
- Introduce himself.
Here. Okay.
- There we go.
And then let me,
do you know how to make this slideshow?
Let's see.
- Who knows the quick prompt to get the PDF to show up?
- That's an excellent question.
Let's see here.
- Close your tools. - Yeah. Oh.
- There you go. There you go.
- All right.
And then.
- Oh, is it not showing? - No.
Let me try to enter.
Let's see.
- We'll get the slideshow in a moment here
as soon as we get our engineering expert
to figure out the tech.
(Pavan and Josh laugh)
- All right, let's see.
I mean, they're present here.
Let's see.
- You're sharing via Zoom? - Yeah.
- Here's the solution. - Yeah.
- So we'll stop our screen share here.
- And then we'll just do the window.
- Yeah. - Yeah, that's-
- There you go. You know what you're doing.
- Yeah. - Yeah.
So hit that red stop button first.
- Yeah.
- Oh, there it is, there.
- There you go. - Yeah.
- All right.
It's on Zoom anyhow.
That's, yeah, Acrobat.
It's...
Let's see.
- One second, one second.
- You know what I can do?
I'm gonna go-
- I think view full screen mode might be there.
- It's...
Yeah, exactly.
It's on Acrobat.
All right, let me try.
- There you go. - Do we know finder here?
It's...
Let me try the PowerPoint version instead.
- There you go. PowerPoint version.
- Then let me go here.
Okay.
Oh, yeah. Okay.
- Oh, yeah Zoom should be screened too, I think.
And then it's just, you just slideshow
to the screens.
I think when you start.
- Yeah. - There you go. There you go.
- Yeah.
- When you start the slideshow,
it automatically goes as well.
- Okay. There.
- Slideshow there.
Start.
There we go.
- There we go. All right.
- So for the educators in the room which is-
- Takes a little bit, right? - Yeah.
- All right.
Well, thanks guys.
Appreciate it, Josh.
I'm Pavan Yedavalli.
I lead our system simulation
and product intelligence efforts at Wisk Aero.
So I'll be like fairly focused here
and talk about what Wisk does.
And generally how we're really looking at the future
of advanced air mobility as it relates
to workforce development,
and really the future of what we hope, you know,
transportation to look like in the coming decades.
So with that being said,
Wisk, we are essentially building autonomous,
fully autonomous, electric vertical takeoff
and landing aircraft.
So there are,
and what I mean by that is we are purely doing
passenger aircraft and that's what we're developing
our aircraft for right now.
And the whole idea is that we want to create a future
where there's autonomous aircraft carrying people
across major metro areas like the Bay Area, for instance,
across the world.
And the whole idea is to really try to bring people,
communities, aviation, all together in one beautiful,
beautiful, you know, combination of
what new mobility might look like.
So, you know, the goal in our mission is really
to deliver safe everyday flight for everyone.
So just kind of going into what autonomous eVTOLs are.
So autonomy is obviously without a pilot,
and the eVTOL part is actually,
that's short for electric vertical takeoff and landing.
So what we're developing as our aircraft,
which you see right there,
is we are trying to develop an aircraft
that does not require any runways,
but instead can just vertically take off and land
and it does all of this fully autonomously.
So the whole idea behind that,
obviously safety is number one.
You know, the, we are trying to build an aircraft
and an operation that is to 10 to the minus nine
safety levels, which is even more than
what current commercial aviation does to this day.
And that is the safest mode of transportation
there is on Earth, (laughs)
by seat mile.
And of course outside of safety, you know,
very sustainable.
And the goal at scale is to make it
as affordable as possible.
Well, obviously we're focusing on
going toward passenger transport first,
which we obviously believe is not only challenging,
but you know, hopefully the holy grail as well.
We are looking into other use cases as well.
Cargo, medical emergency services,
as Cody will certainly talk about representing Joby.
You know, piloted operations are expected soon.
So very, very exciting there.
So we're gonna really see this industry start to grow
and start to understand how folks are riding on the aircraft
and what sort of benefit advanced air mobility will give.
Autonomous operations of Wisk in particular
will really start shortly thereafter.
So we're kind of going directly to autonomy.
And just at the bottom here, there's a lot of potential.
A lot of folks are really, really excited about
what the future of advanced air mobility will do
to society, to communities,
and ultimately to adding well paying,
well paying jobs and contribute to economic output.
So just kind of putting into perspective a couple of,
a couple of numbers here.
By 2035, we're expecting up to 280,000 well paying jobs
across the US.
So with that being said, Wisk,
I'll quickly go into a very, very quick history.
We started off as Larry Page's,
Larry Page, one of the founders of Google,
a bit of his pet project
almost 15 years ago as Zee.Aero.
And from there, over time we started developing
many generations of aircraft,
which I'll get into in just a moment.
But now to this day, we are,
we became a joint venture
between Boeing and Kitty Hawk several years ago.
And then just a couple of years ago,
we became a fully,
wholly owned independent subsidiary of Boeing.
So with all that, with this decade of experience,
we've actually flown thousands of test flights
of our different generations of aircraft.
So, you know, issued hundreds of patents.
We have employees across the world, predominantly here.
Our headquarters are in Mountain View,
but we have folks in Canada, in Poland,
in New Zealand and Australia.
So just a quick history of flight.
You know, we started with our Gen 1,
which was back in 2011
and started developing that?
This was a smaller aircraft but fully autonomous.
And you can kind of see that we jumped across generations
up to our Gen 5 aircraft between autonomous and piloted.
As you can imagine, there are so many different,
different learnings that we can gain
from having both versions so that we can understand
what the most optimal solution would be
for an autonomous aircraft ultimately.
So we've flown Gen 5, which is our Cora aircraft,
thousands of times.
And it's been very, very exciting
to take those learnings into what our current aircraft
that we're developing is,
which is our Wisk Generation 6 aircraft.
So this is intended to be the first
FAA certified commercial autonomous passenger aircraft.
So just a couple of specs here on this aircraft.
It's autonomous, but autonomy doesn't mean, you know,
set it and forget it.
As hopefully, you know,
being all in the Bay Area right now,
hopefully at some point folks have been able to take Waymo's
maybe in San Francisco.
I know it's happening in San Jose now,
but the whole idea is there's remote supervision.
A lot of supervision of the aircraft,
constant communication with the aircraft.
So there's constant human oversight.
Our, the capacity of the aircraft is four people.
The dimensions, you know, we have about a 50 foot,
well a little less than 50 feet in wingspan.
The range of the aircraft is about 90 miles.
So that covers the bulk of the Bay Area,
you know, our nine county Bay Area.
So it's, and I'll jump into the,
what we're seeing in the Bay Area itself,
but there's a lot of potential to carry people in the,
with the goal of having them save time
or, you know, provide a unique experience altogether.
And then, because it's all electric,
so that's the e part of the eVTOL,
we expect the infrastructure which are known as vertiports.
We expect that those will be charging, you know,
in just a few minutes, up to 15 minutes.
And then off to the next, off to the next.
So the, if you can imagine a little bit of,
and this is kind of in my,
in my dream world, you know?
We have a lot of dense infrastructure sites,
not dissimilar to a subway network, you know,
maybe not that many,
but, you know, very, very much
a beautiful marriage
between public transit right now and aviation.
'Cause obviously we're gonna have a lot of,
a lot of work with,
with everything associated with aviation
and things to do at the infrastructure sites.
So why autonomy?
Monisha actually touched on it as well.
So there's safety.
Safety is, you know, first and foremost, you know,
the bulk of accidents right now are often due to,
due to errors that are occurring due to the humans.
You know, it's also relate to scalability?
You know, at scale it will bring costs down?
And then, you know, it's maintenance.
Ultimately the aircraft will be significantly easier
to maintain over time.
So one thing we really focus on here at Wisk
is accessibility, and this is accessibility for the riders
as well as those, you know, at infrastructure itself.
So we do a lot of work
with those who are disabled,
we get a lot of user research about
what the experience needs to be
to accommodate a good experience for everyone.
So you can see here, you know,
we've brought people into our,
into our headquarters,
actually have them test out our aircraft
to see exactly what are the pain points,
how do we improve the design.
And similarly, you know, things relate to accessibility
as we kind of take an Uber right now
or a Lyft right now or a Waymo.
You know, we'll probably have something similar
where we're using our phones to schedule a flight?
And, you know, trying to understand what exactly
that user experience should be is very, very important.
So very, very quickly on the regional benefits of AAM.
You know, the whole idea again is to augment
the transportation network?
A lot of my research actually at UC Berkeley
was trying to understand what the impacts of AAM are
on metropolitan environments.
And the reality is that we are going to see
that this will be a very, very valuable mode
to the overarching transportation network.
But it's not necessarily going to relieve the congestion
that we see on 101 or on 880 every day.
What we do hope to do is we intend to have it
actually provide a service that is very much necessary
to allow for longer distance travel for very short times.
So in the end, it still took almost an hour 20 for me
to come from San Francisco down to Santa Clara.
In an ideal world that would be cut down significantly
and maybe there, and there's an opportunity for that.
So community time, reducing pressure on
existing infrastructure.
And the last couple of things that are very much related
to today is workforce development.
So just looking at the Bay area very quickly,
and this is a lot of the work
that my team does is relate to software simulation
and demand modeling to understand
where we should place our infrastructure
and what sort of benefit this will provide for riders.
So you can see that in the Bay area, you know,
we could have almost, you know,
several hundred thousand passengers per day
who may take this, you know, obviously at the service level
who, what we can actually serve based on our fleet sizes
and things of that nature, based on infrastructure
will be significantly lower than that.
But just to show exactly what the potential
of AAM is in the Bay Area is significant.
And obviously you can imagine other places like New York,
Tokyo, Chicago, LA, we're starting to talk about,
you know, a really, really valuable mode of transportation.
So I'll just end on a couple of things
that we've been working on at Wisk
and in particular in California.
We did a case study down in LA in the Long Beach Area
with Cal State Long Beach.
And essentially it was an economic development study
that we did in tandem with Cal State Long Beach.
And what we found is we wanted to understand the impact,
the economic development impact of developing AAM
as part of the transportation network down in LA.
And so there were several different areas of opportunity
where jobs will be created,
good, nice, well paying jobs that will require
enormous amount of training,
but also a great amount of
potential knowledge in a variety of industries.
So, you know, in construction, at scale
we're talking about over 2,000 jobs
annually from operations at the vertiports themselves.
We're talking about maintenance,
the passenger experience, terminal facilities,
all of these things not dissimilar
to commercial aviation today.
We're gonna need some level of that
at the infrastructure that is being developed.
So that's on the infrastructure side
and obviously on the aircraft side we're talking about
operations with air traffic management,
with ATC, all these things are actually
going to be enormous opportunities for jobs.
And one thing I'll mention
is we just as we're starting to see a lot of the, you know,
generative AI, these types of things
really coming into our lexicon,
a little bit about how jobs are shifting.
Now, what we're finding is exactly that,
is that there are going to be new versions
of jobs while we focus on autonomy,
there's going to be a significant requirement
for other skill sets and other knowledge.
And that's what we're trying to understand
and work toward as well.
So we're very, very excited
down in Long Beach in particular.
We hosted Long Beach Community College students
and really talked about what the potential
is for contributing to this industry in the coming decades.
So, you know, this is just a start
and we're really trying to get everyone very much involved
and excited about what advanced air mobility
and autonomous advanced air mobility is in the future.
So I'll end there and yeah, very, very excited
and very honored to be here to talk
a little bit more about the industry.
So, thank you.
(attendees applaud)
- Thank you, Pavan.
And next we will have our colleague Cody Cleverly from Joby.
- Thank you, enjoy your thing.
All right, we'll see if Zoom cooperates again here.
We went way off the rails,
I think for some good reasons a few minutes ago.
So give me a second.
And as I get this deck pulled up,
I'm gonna also go way off script here
because there's a lot of similarities
across our three companies,
which is I think a trend that is really important
for you all to see as educators.
Let's see, I've lost Zoom.
- Do you start slideshow?
It will- - Yes.
- Well it would, it would've before
we changed the settings,
but it's working now.
Yeah. Cool.
Good, so I'm gonna go off script here
and highlight some key facts that kind of build on
what my colleagues and my competitors talk to you about.
I can't believe, I can't believe they even let us sit
next to each other up here.
(all laughing)
In fact, I was untying his shoes while he was trying,
getting ready to stand up
to see if I could embarrass him a little bit
before he came up here.
But I think one thing I want you to all take away
as educators about this industry
is that it's a huge emerging industry
that's gonna absolutely change our world in tremendous ways.
And it's represented by the fact that there's three
of us in an industry full of players
who are advancing this new sector of aerospace.
And I'll also emphasize from a workforce standpoint,
what's incredible about this new sector of aviation
and aerospace is it in no way cannibalizes
the existing industry in almost no ways,
in very, very small ways.
For example, you know, the regional airlines,
the large airlines like Delta and United,
they're gonna continue doing what they're doing.
The concepts that we are talking about here,
and we use the term advanced air mobility
or urban air mobility to really illustrate, you know,
this urban ride sharing service, which is ultimately
what the three of us have our site set on, right?
As Monisha shared, you know, crop dusting
and these other really important things
are an important part of the industry segment.
But ultimately passenger carriage
is where the bulk of the industry is going.
And that creates demand for air transportation
that has never existed in human history
and thus creates demand for extra jobs
that haven't existed before in aerospace and aviation.
And it's happening right here in California,
particularly on the Central Coast and in the Bay Area,
as you're seeing from those of us
who are here to share about our companies.
So I'll go quick through Joby
so that you just get a broad perspective
of kind of what's happening in the industry.
Joby is a pretty large player in the space
with over 2,000 employees,
primarily between San Carlos and Marina, California
and the Monterey Peninsula
and growing considerably.
So if you go to our website,
you'll see that we have hundreds of job posted today
for your graduates that are coming out of your,
out of your programs.
We're vertically integrated transportation company.
And really what that means is we do virtually
everything in house.
So rather than, you know, typically an aerospace,
an aircraft OEM or original equipment manufacturer
will outsource as much of the aircraft as they can,
and they'll kind of assemble it together
into an aircraft design and then sell it to operators.
At Joby we've decided to bring all of that in house.
So if you go to that third line there,
we develop test manufacturer and it says soon we'll operate,
and I guess soon we'll operate it commercially.
But we're already operating our aircraft in partnership
with the Department of Defense.
And what that vertical integration means for all of you
and for all of us in this region
and across the state from a workforce standpoint,
is there is a tremendous diversity of jobs
that are coming up in this industry for graduates
of the community college system.
So we have a,
it looks like I have a font issue there,
but we have a core aircraft product
that we've developed over the last 15 years
that kind of serves as our flagship product
that we think will help
along with my colleagues here at the other companies
to help pioneer this air taxi industry.
And our aircraft,
unlike the ones you heard about before,
is a piloted aircraft.
So we've made the choice to bring a piloted aircraft
to market for a host of regulatory
and public acceptance reasons, right?
So that kind of goes without saying
and we're thrilled, I'm thrilled
that you are pushing the limits on autonomy safely.
So thank you.
So that when our autonomy division,
Joby has an autonomy division,
we fly aircraft autonomously on conventional platforms
so that this aircraft that you see here
that's piloted either will have a variant
a few years down the line
that's autonomous or this aircraft
will see block upgrades to be autonomous as well.
So I think I'm illustrating
that even though Joby, you know, you hear about
what we're doing if you go read our press releases,
while we're launching a piloted aircraft,
we have our site set on autonomy as well.
So it kind of illustrates where this industry is going
in the context of everything you're hearing
about over the next few days.
But similar to what you've heard,
it's an all electric aircraft,
it takes off and lands vertically,
100 mile range.
So that really doubles down
on the urban air mobility mission, right?
We're not talking about flying from one end
of the state of California to the other,
we're talking about connecting people inside the Bay Area.
We're talking about connecting the Bay to the Bay, right?
And that's really where all of this traffic is.
So I'll play this video to kind of try
to give you a visual picture of the diversity of jobs
that I talked about in this industry
and specifically at Joby, in this case.
(upbeat music)
(upbeat music continues)
Okay, so I'll skip some of this go to market stuff
and I'll hit a few key points
so we can get into the meat of the panel here.
But we're talking about flying taxis, right?
That's ultimately what this business segment is all about.
And so, you know, in a few years you'll be,
you'll expect a similar experience
that you have with Uber or Lyft for air taxis.
In fact, we have key operational partnerships
and investments from both Delta and Uber
who are key operational partners.
And we'll be integrated into the Uber app.
So you'll be able to book a Joby in the Uber app.
You'll be able to book a,
an Uber in the Joby app ultimately creating
what we call a seamless multimodal ride sharing experience.
So here's an example of a route network
to kind of get into the meat and potatoes
of what's the actual experience going to look like.
This is an example in New York City
and this route starts at the downtown heliport
in Manhattan and arrives at JFK Airport in Queens.
So that's a seven minute flight in a Joby aircraft.
And by car, well we're saying 49 minutes,
raise your hand if you've driven from Manhattan to JFK.
Okay, we've got some people.
Somebody shout it out, how long does it take
to drive from JFK to Manhattan?
- [Attendee] Hour and a half.
- Hour and a half is what everyone's saying.
Okay, good.
Yeah, rush hour, which is most of the day,
sometimes over two hours, right?
Yeah, 49 minutes is at 2:00 AM
and miraculously all the potholes were repaired, right?
Just before you drove this route.
But this illustrates how tremendous
the time savings really are
by bringing travel into the third dimension.
And that's really why this, why this industry segment,
why it was, why we're creating these products.
And this is an example just building on the Wisk slide
of what a route network might look like in the Bay Area
to connect, like I said, the Bay to the Bay.
'Cause the issue, you know,
getting around the Bay is the real problem.
Getting across the Bay is the real problem, right?
And so bringing people into the,
into the skies is a key part of that experience.
Of course, like I said, it's a piloted aircraft
that carries up to four passengers.
And I had another slide in here
that didn't transfer from my USB drive.
Well that actually played some audio
of how quiet the aircraft is.
It didn't work.
So you'll have to go to YouTube
and watch some YouTube videos.
We also actually just launched an iPhone app
called Joby Sounds where you can download the app
and hear our aircraft
with different urban backgrounds
and things in the background.
You can compare it to helicopters, which is always fun.
To hear how much quieter electric aircraft
can be when they're designed properly.
But you know, you know, we got some academics in here.
So decimals are a logarithmic scale, right?
Orders of magnitude difference in sound.
And so, you know, the Joby aircraft is fewer
than 50 decibels at 700 feet flying overhead
compared to a comparable size helicopter at 65 decibels.
And for those of you who vacuum,
raise your hand if you've ever used a vacuum.
Yeah, okay.
Some of you're staring at me like I'm not gonna
raise my hand.
(attendees laugh)
'Cause we all know you've never vacuumed,
most of you, but a vacuum puts out 75 decibels, right?
So when you vacuum your living room,
you're exposed to more decibels
than our aircraft will expose you
to flying over urban cities across the world.
And there's my video that I thought I took out
that's broken, so find it on YouTube.
You'll be glad you did.
Again, just to kind of double down on the fact
that these are real jobs right here in our backyard.
This is the Joby footprint.
There's a few of our facilities aren't on this map
because they're small and growing facilities.
But our four primary facilities, San Carlos,
so closest to home here is where we do our powertrain
and electronics manufacturing.
So it's where we make all of our batteries,
all of our electric motors,
all of our circuit boards,
all of our flight computers, et cetera.
Santa Cruz is our headquarters
and we have some R&D work happening in Santa Cruz as well.
We have a training academy in Watsonville,
where we train pilots and mechanics.
Public offering for folks with zero experience in aviation.
They can come into our academy
and learn to become a pilot or a mechanic.
And then in Marina, down near Monterey
is where we're actually manufacturing our aircraft.
We've ramped capacity to about 12 aircraft per year
at that facility.
And we'll double that capacity in the next 12 to 18 months
there in Marina.
And all of that's happening in California.
And over 80% of the aircraft components
are made right here in our backyard,
hopefully in the next few years by your graduates.
And I'm actually gonna stop there
so we can get into the panel
because I want to hear what you want
to know about this industry.
And actually we're not getting into the panel,
we're getting into the best part,
but I don't wanna prolong,
I don't wanna prolong things any further.
- Thanks. Thanks, Cody.
(attendees applaud)
Yeah, so with all these great companies growing here,
there's just a couple of things I would like to point out
is that all of this is in such early stages
and you've heard each of them talk about the longer vision.
So I think the opportunity for growth is like,
it's a new renaissance in the aviation
for the Bay Area and for California.
So really exciting time and it hadn't
and it wouldn't have happened as well
or as quickly without UC Berkeley
and other key research institutions here.
So, Go Bears. - Go Bears.
(attendees applaud)
- And I'd like to introduce Dr. Jasenka Rakas
who's gonna tell you all about
some of the exciting things happening up there.
Let's end this and you can get into your thing.
- It's called...
Here.
- This one? - No, no.
- This one? - Yeah.
- And let me see if I can do this.
Boom.
- Thank you. - Okay.
- Hello, everyone.
And thank you for your patience.
You can see how competitors can be nice and civilized here.
(all laughing) (attendees applaud)
And so,
yes, they do deserve a round of applause.
So why am I here?
Well, UC Berkeley is a state university
and UC Berkeley has a very good reputation
and history about working with community colleges.
And personally because I teach aviation courses,
I teach sustainable aviation and infrastructure
and airport systems design.
Students who transfer to our engineering program
from community colleges are usually at that,
well, this is a senior undergrad classes.
They are the most enthusiastic, the most resourceful,
the most eager to learn and create
and often the most innovative.
So in light of that,
we will be also discussing how further UC Berkeley
and our Institute of Transportation Studies.
And what I'm going to talk about
is our UC Berkeley Mobility Hub
at one of our facilities at Richmond Field Station.
All working together hopefully to bring
and to collaborate with community colleges
and to bring and transfer
more of these young talents into our engineering program.
Our, as you know, by reputation,
UC Berkeley is the world renowned university
as ranked number one public university in the world.
Our engineering program is ranked number one
and our students really, as you get to Berkeley
and near these engineering schools,
you can get that vibe and that energy
and enthusiasm that comes with these young bright minds.
So to support all of that and to support
and collaborate on this
new innovative way of bringing
or transporting people through emerging concepts
such as urban air mobility.
Urban air mobility is just one
of the emerging concepts
that further transport people.
And our UC Berkeley Mobility Hub,
which was recently created at the Richmond Field Station,
which is a property of UC Berkeley,
very close to Berkeley but in Richmond,
which was created not that long ago,
is a part of our Institute of Transportation Studies.
And our institute is the oldest
and our transportation libraries, the oldest in the country.
Our students spent, transportation students,
engineering students spent long hours there studying
and working on their homework assignments
and term projects.
But the ITS as a big institute
under now the guidance
and leadership of Justin Wiley,
who is our strategy and development director.
And Justin is right in the back as a boss, yes please.
And you will be hearing from him during
probably the last part of this session
and during the break about
all these exciting opportunities that UC Berkeley
is now having with community colleges.
This 140 acre now piece of land
is more than just simple Richmond Field Station
for advancing transportation and advancing mobility.
This new Berkeley Mobility Hub
serves as a real world test bed,
and not only for one type of research and operations,
UC Berkeley is well known for connected
and autonomous vehicles design
and system that connects them.
At this mobility hub,
we further develop zero emissions vehicles
and new energy sources.
Hydrogen is a big innovation area
that ITS researchers are working on
through various research centers
that are under the Institute of Transportation Studies.
We have research trust at the Berkeley Mobility Hub
about public transportation and shared mobility
about fleet, freight and logistics
and then advanced aviation,
anything from drones, eVTOLs.
And you heard from our developers
what kind of eVTOLs we have,
how different concepts can be used
to bring these eVTOLs into the city
and regional fabric.
Because one side of the story
is to develop a vehicle,
well you have to develop a system
and then you have to actually bring
that system into your communities.
And as with the noise,
when we originally started building airports,
that wasn't a big problem.
Citizens who live south of LAX Airport
and El Segundo were powerful enough
to stop the expansion of, and the number of gates at LAX
because of the noise issues.
So my point is that it is extremely important to work
with your communities to get their approval
of your new concepts.
And although the aircraft might be very quiet,
maybe visual pollution might be another problem.
So working with these communities,
as I said would be very important.
We also have research on connected
and digital infrastructure
and that is basically an underlying
piece of infrastructure that enables flights
of drones or eVTOLs or connected vehicles.
So these are some of the new facilities,
new automated vehicle test track,
new signal lab, new drone park training facility.
And with all these facilities
under the leadership now of Justin,
Berkeley's position, again as a global center
for next generation mobility research,
how to make it into the real world and make it to commercial
and how to create a workforce.
And we have also through the ITS
various other initiatives
where our knowledge can be transferred
into the real world where our former students
are now leaders at one of these eVTOLs developer companies.
So as I said, this is the very unique university
that welcomes community college students.
It is very famous for what we call the social mobility,
students from, at our university
often come as students from underprivileged backgrounds,
a large percentage of students are actually
first generation college students.
And that gives that diversity
and that enthusiasm brings us
to that next level where we are now,
where we are the best public university in the world.
Our UC Berkeley Mobility Hub
is now this unique opportunity
to fill this growing industry need
for advanced vehicle testing
across different transportation verticals and modes.
And this hub creates a scalable ecosystem
for research, commercialization
and workforce development.
And that benefits the university, our partners,
and more importantly the public
because we are the public university
and we are very much aware of it
because it is your tax payer's,
tax money that we live on.
So we are trying to make the best out of it.
Thank you.
(attendees applaud)
I wanted to also just share with you this link.
We will be having on October 23rd and the 24th,
AI mobility workshop.
And Justin might share maybe during the panel discussion
a few words about this workshop.
Thanks. (attendees applaud)
- All right.
Thank you, Jasenka.
Well I would love to invite you all to the panel discussion,
but we've had such a great set of talks
that we have actually expended our time for the panel.
So what I would like to invite you to do,
some of us will stick around
and as some of us have calls to run off to,
but some of us will stick around
and we'd love to take questions over here on the side
if that's something you want to do or out in the lobby.
If this, we can stay here?
So we can stay here.
Maybe if, can we keep talking, if we can stay here?
Well if anyone has to leave to the next session,
you may do so.
But if you would like to stick around here,
it doesn't seem like we have to run out right away
so we can take a couple of questions
or comments from the audience.
Does that sound right?
Sir?
- First off, I wanna thank you for your panel.
I'm with (faintly speaking) for the workforce board.
We work very close to our community college partners.
I've worked in multiple states before
and in supporting aviation programs,
the A&P, the Airframe and Powerplant license
is a very common credential
that colleges and workforce boards can really focus on,
produce a skilled town pipeline.
Do you foresee any equivalency to that
where one program can meet multiple employer needs?
It really kind of helps, I think leverage a lot of synergy
around training workforce and employer needs.
Thank you.
- You wanna start?
- No, go ahead.
- Okay.
Can you guys hear me okay? Good.
Yeah, this is, I actually had a slide on this.
One of the slides I skipped was about this very issue.
So all of you have heard about the pilot shortage, right?
In the mainstream media there's not enough pilots,
not enough pilots.
It's true.
I'm a pilot and Joby only hired me
'cause there weren't enough of me, right?
So I'm lucky,
I'm a lucky recipient of the shortage.
But the mechanic shortage is far worse,
even though there's not mainstream media coverage
for the mechanic shortage.
And even my colleagues here
who are developing autonomous aircraft
need a lot of mechanics, right?
So there's a huge pain across the industry already.
And as I said before, we're creating, you know-
- Slides.
- Oh, thank you, thank you.
Josh knows my slides well.
So this represents Oliver Wyman's study
that shows that by I think 2027,
they're predicting a shortage of 8,000 mechanics
across the US.
And this does not take into account
the advanced air mobility industry
that we just described to you today.
So this is just our conventional aviation industry.
So the reality is there's a huge gap there already.
The other reality is that
the Airframe and Powerplant certification
is a federal aviation administration certification.
You cannot, you're not authorized
to perform maintenance on an aircraft
without this certification.
You have to have it.
The problem is it doesn't teach
anything about electric aircraft.
So there's a big gap there.
But the other problem is there, you know,
I don't know if there's any community colleges, Gavilan
or quest to college
closest in our region here in the room,
but the, they don't have room in their curriculum
to add anything about electric aircraft
because of the nature of the FAA requirements.
And so there's, you know, a lot of work
that needs to go into there.
What we know needs to happen
is we need more academic institutions
creating aircraft mechanics who have that certification.
And then we need more industry partnerships
with academic institutions, nonprofits, and others
to bring that additional electric aircraft training,
like the advanced manufacturing
or the advanced maintenance technician
apprenticeship program that DART created
in partnership with Joby
to create an apprenticeship path
to both the Airframe and Powerplant certification
and the electric aircraft training
that allows technicians over two and a half years
to get all that training while they earn and learn
on the job training.
So more to discuss there for sure. It's a huge issue.
- Yeah, absolutely.
And I'll quickly double down on
what Cody was saying
and add a little bit more from that autonomy piece as well.
You know, just in that electric powertrain,
electric mechanic for aircraft,
we're obviously gonna have another aspect of that
that's really related to autonomy integration technicians
and things of that nature that are like basically
very, very much tied into the operation
of the aircraft itself.
That will very much be a new occupation altogether
that we're kind of trying to understand and develop now.
So that's yet another aspect of it
that I'll just quickly add.
Thanks.
- [Josh] We have another question here.
You can see if there's a microphone.
- There's a button on the bottom
that you have to press and hold.
Long press.
Yeah, long press till you see a green light.
And then flip the switch near the top too.
- Nice.
- I can't figure out Zoom,
but I know how to work myself
around a microphone, that's for sure.
- [Attendee] Well.
- We can hear you. - Yeah, we can hear you.
- So I was thinking,
given the shortage and how long it takes us
to actually build up a program in our community colleges,
what do you see as potentials of transferable paths
that would lead into some of your workforce needs
as well as, you know, one of the things
that would be nice similar to the apprenticeship route
would be almost like a bridge to your industry?
So we have advanced manufacturing,
we have our automotive programs
that are in electrical, autonomous space
that we're, you know, moving into
and getting students through.
Can those then lead into something
that we would then be able to partner with?
- I think so many of the things and the people
you're already training are extremely valuable
for a lot of roles at our companies.
I think like some of the skills that I talked with
a number of my leaders about what are the skills
that you're most looking for in people
to enter into our technician, operator, engineering,
honestly all roles.
And some of the kind of critical things
they talked about are practical problem solving,
creating simple solutions to complex problems,
ability to work in fast-paced learning environments.
So flexibility, adapting to kind of changed,
like changing requirements and such.
And then hands-on skills and experience.
And I really want to emphasize the hands-on skills
and experience, like everyone I talk to
and every role I've hired for essentially,
that is working on the plane in any capacity
is looking for what have you actually built,
what have you actually assembled?
So I think, and we look to not just
what you're doing in school, but also projects in your own.
So I think the, like, the more you can, for us at least,
or my experience is the more you can get people out
of just theory and actually building
and assembling things, fixing things,
kind of debugging things
and encouraging project work on their own, the better.
Like if, you know, people take time to work on their bike,
motorcycle, build something at home, yeah.
Those are some skills that are really valuable.
- That's great. - Yeah.
- The community colleges are your best friend.
- Totally.
Totally.
- So I think the challenge though,
if I look at your job descriptions,
because I opened up some of 'em.
- Yeah.
- Each of your conversations,
they all require three to five years of some experience
in your industry.
So how do we translate all of the skills
that students are building in our programs
that are technical, that are hands-on,
might be in electrical tech,
it might be in advanced manufacturing,
it might be, you know, to get into your industry.
That's the challenge.
- That's-
- [Attendee] We would love to partner with you.
- That's a really great question
and I, yeah, I am really excited about the idea of,
and I need to talk to somebody.
I would definitely need like the buy-in
of some of the managers on those teams,
but I know they're excited about the potential
of having like internship or co-op programs.
And I think like having a partner of a college,
like I'm excited to be here
and hopefully just have exposure to people knowing me
to build partnerships where people in colleges,
like, are actually partners in
creating exposure and being excited.
(attendee faintly speaking)
- Like, great.
- [Attendee] Talk to them, you should.
- Pam was just telling me about it.
College of Alameda? Great.
- [Attendee] Hi, you already, you are doing that,
you're doing that right now.
You're partnered with us on a project
where community college students are gonna get to do that.
- Amazing.
(Monisha laughs)
- [Attendee] Tell you more about what we're doing.
(all laughing)
- Great. Thank you.
- [Josh] And I would just take a moment
to mention some of the work that we've been
able to do down in Monterey in this regard,
has really been about addressing
exactly what you're talking about.
And through apprenticeship model has really worked well.
And we've also worked with the workforce board
to do internship programs
and increasingly with each of the community colleges
to align kind of short-term work experience,
opportunities that meet the need
that Joby and other players have down there.
So-
- [Attendee] Yeah, I'm in Southern California
so anybody wants to go to Orange County?
- [Josh] Yeah.
So we're talking to your Orange County business people.
- [Attendee] 'Cause I think it's really hard
for you to finish it from down there about.
- [Josh] Yeah, yeah.
We've just been having good conversations
with the Orange County Business Council
and also the South Coast Workforce Investment Board
has some really good stuff going on in that regard.
- I wanna add one more thing to that question
'cause I think it's actually something
that is I'm passionate about,
is getting people of different backgrounds
and underrepresented populations into the workforce.
And I definitely being in an industry
that is, I would love to see more diversity
in the pipeline coming in.
One of the messages that I really want
to get out more is encouraging
and for us all to encourage people who don't check all
of the boxes to still apply.
I think like it's rare to find candidates
who check every single box.
So we, like, write preferred qualifications
and we've started shifting to doing preferred
and required, so it's a little more clear, like,
which are actually really necessary to have.
But establishing and really encouraging students
to apply to things, even if they don't check all the boxes.
And recognizing that it tends to shift
towards underrepresented populations
who don't apply to things
that they don't check all the boxes for.
So like all collectively kind of getting
that message out I think is really important.
And then I think like adding into resumes, you know,
projects and such outside of just the careers
that you've done.
And yeah, I mean for,
I actually haven't seen portfolios really
for technician role and operator roles
for a mech, like engineering roles.
We really value portfolios
and portfolios that show project work,
things that you've actually built.
And so, yeah, I don't know.
I haven't talked about the idea
of adding portfolios into some of those other roles,
but in my head right now I'm like,
I think that would go a long way
for our hiring managers to see,
oh, you've actually built and made things on your own,
even if not in this specific profession.
- [Attendee] That's really cool. Thank you.
- [Josh] That's great.
Cody, do you want to add anything to that
based on your experience
with the way you frame the recruitments and things?
- Sure, I'll briefly address,
specifically what you said about advanced manufacturing.
I think, one thing that we have going against us
in California, as everyone says,
you can't manufacture things in California.
And for a long time we all believed that it was true.
And I think what we're finding down in Monterey County
and San Mateo County for that matter
with our aircraft manufacturing,
is that we started manufacturing in California
as a measure of necessity,
co-located with our R&D efforts
because we didn't have time
to spool up manufacturing elsewhere.
We didn't have time.
Turns out manufacturing in California
works really well if you have the support systems in place.
And so what I would love to see
is more advanced manufacturing programs
at the community colleges
with an engineering lens, right?
So they're not necessarily engineering degrees,
but where people really get accustomed
to building things and the hardware.
And so, you know, we're all excited about AI,
that's why we're all here,
but we're also all terrified about AI, right?
Because of the job loss that's inevitable
and it's also gonna make our world
a better place in many ways.
One antidote to that that Silicon Valley really needs
to further embrace is hardware, right?
So when you have aircraft
or other hardware, you need people to make that stuff.
And yeah, there's advanced robotics and other things,
but the point is people with hardware competence
are a lot more competitive for these jobs.
And as this industry industry continues
to vertically integrate, like I talked about
with Joby's business model,
we have many, many, many manufacturing technicians
with some of those technical competencies
for engineering, moving into engineering roles
without a four-year degree.
And we like them better than some
of the four-year degree graduates
who have no experience with manufacturing
because they can hit the ground running
providing engineering support to the manufacturing teams.
- So we got one other question here and one over there
and then maybe we can wrap.
- [Mike] Sure.
Mike Roberts, I'm with Creating Coding Careers.
We are building the playbook for company driven
earn and learn pathways.
So one of the things I do a lot of work
with is apprenticeship degree pathways.
One of our partners is Foothill.
We also have four year partners
like Western Governors University.
And I'm curious, one of the populations we serve a lot of
are transitioning service members.
Folks that have military experience,
they're within their last six months.
We have a Skillbridge program where they can come
skill bridge, be reassigned their duty to train,
and we put them on a pathway for apprenticeships
and apprenticeship degrees.
I'm curious if any of you have experience working
with transitioning service members
and if you think that that population aligns
with some of the experience that you're looking for.
And then your thoughts on apprenticeship degrees in general.
- I can quickly touch on it.
To my knowledge, I'm not entirely sure
whether Wisk has a formal program for that,
but given what we know about
how we're developing the aircraft
and the operations, having a former military background
is absolutely invaluable to what we can do.
And the reason for that obviously is having real operational
and manufacturing capabilities
as well as being able to use the systems
that are being developed
and understanding exactly
what the fail-safes are versus not.
So one thing that I'll, you know,
pretty, pretty bluntly say
is that autonomy is in the military right now, right?
It has been in the military for a long time.
So the usage of autonomy in different ways
is going to be kind of the future.
How do we use it for specific applications?
And so even having a grounded understanding
of how autonomous aircraft work,
autonomous ground-based vehicles work,
that is incredibly valuable for us
and for the industry moving forward.
And so I would say that's one aspect of it.
The other aspect of it is obviously just having
extensive experience with aircraft in general,
pilots, operational technician,
maintenance, these are all things
that will continue to remain, as Cody was mentioning,
in electric vertical takeoff and landing aircraft,
in autonomous eVTOLs, in autonomous CTOLs.
Everything in the future of aviation will still require
many of those jobs that have already been essentially
perfected by many military folks.
So to that extent, I think it's,
now is a perfect opportunity to start thinking about
how to build that pipeline for apprenticeships.
So absolutely.
- I have a critical word of caution.
So we hired dozens of Skillbridge folks
through Skillbridge every year,
and you can, you would expect that we have, you know,
a huge pipeline of military folks.
People talk about how challenging the transition
from military to civilian is
because it really, really is extremely challenging.
And the harsh reality is that
these startup environments are in some cases the worst
place for folks coming straight out of the military.
You go from, and I, you know, I've had former,
I don't have a military background,
I've had many service members work on my team
and report to me and in their first few weeks
and months when they ask me what I want them to do
and I say, well here's the problem, what do you think?
Like their brain, like short circuits, right?
Because they're used to being told like what to do, right?
And in these egalitarian startup environments,
that is not how we operate very often.
And so I think the message there would be, you know,
I think a lot of times employers think about Skillbridge
and other programs as like a try it before you buy it,
let's see if this works.
And if we like this person and then bring them on full time,
we should be coaching service members
to look at it the same way.
And seize those opportunities to give them exposure
to these, like, rapidly moving
highly dynamic environments
so they can decide if that's really the best first step
for them coming out of the service.
And then of course preparing them
and the employers for actually setting people up
for success is another huge challenge.
So I think we have a long way to go
to better supporting service members,
primarily in these startup environments, yeah.
- Nice word of caution.
There's one last question over here,
if you wanna grab the mic.
Maybe you could pass the mic over.
- [Attendee] I'll just use my teacher voice.
- Okay. Use your teacher voice.
- [Attendee] Awesome.
So I was just curious what the interaction level is,
like for autonomous planes, you know, air taxis, et cetera,
with air traffic controllers.
And also considering that there's also a shortage
of air traffic controllers in addition to pilots
as you mentioned and mechanics.
Is there like an industry discussion happening right now?
How to meet those shortages?
- Yeah, now this is an absolutely excellent question
and it's something that we at Wisk are grappling
with on a day-to-day basis.
We're discussing with the FAA,
we're obviously very, very well in tune
with all the NASA UTM work that's occurring.
So air traffic control
and air traffic management is arguably
the most critical aspect of this entire system.
And we've already seen without,
without these futuristic aircraft in the airspace,
things are already getting tougher.
So with all that being said, this is something
that we're thinking about constantly
and we are working to understand exactly
what skills are required,
how to address that ATC shortage you were mentioning,
and where like Wisk and really all the players
in AAM should be positioning themselves
to make that a reality.
What we're finding is, as I was mentioning, you know,
we do remote supervision and that's how we do autonomy.
Remote supervisors, you know, our multi-vehicle supervisors,
these folks will be very, very tied at the hip
to air traffic control.
And to be totally frank,
it's going to be a different type of air traffic management
that we're going to have.
So we're trying to drum up and brainstorm and test
and validate what skills
and what positions will be additionally necessary
for this new airspace.
So all of that is to say we're absolutely looking into it
and that's probably one of the most critical things
that's top of mind.
And this is obviously a huge area of opening
for potential jobs in the industry
that we're very, very aware of.
So it's honestly very, very exciting.
And now is the time that we're trying
to build that pipeline.
- Follow up.
- [Attendee] Just follow up on that, sorry,
I didn't mention my name and background,
(attendee faintly speaking)
education at a college in Long Beach.
And so, you know, if you're having those discussions
and you're not already including colleges at the table
and highly recommend, as one of my colleagues mentioned,
you know, getting us involved.
So I know earlier it was mentioned
that we should create the curriculum.
- Yes.
- [Attendee] Reach out to you guys for
(faintly speaking)
but I would push back a little bit on that
and say, let's have us at the table earlier
and co-create the curriculum to meet their exact needs.
And then also if our students know there are job interviews
waiting at the end of that program,
we're gonna successfully move students
through those programs really quickly.
So that would be my, you know, suggestion
and request for all of us here in the system.
- Absolutely.
And one thing I'll quickly add,
we're working with Berkeley, with NASA,
with other major players in the AAM space
to actually understand what these operations can look like.
Both at early stages and at scale
and then by understanding that a little bit better,
we can get a better picture
of what requirements are necessary, so.
- Fantastic.
Well thank you very much to the panelists.
(attendees applaud)
Thank you, Pam for organizing.
- Thank you, everyone.